<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at North-Hampton the 21. of Iune last past, before the Lord Lieutenant of the county, and the rest of the commissioners there assembled vpon occasion of the late rebellion and riots in those parts committed</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121043</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856232</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856232</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21761</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15386)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21761)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1049:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at North-Hampton the 21. of Iune last past, before the Lord Lieutenant of the county, and the rest of the commissioners there assembled vpon occasion of the late rebellion and riots in those parts committed</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By George Eld] for Iohn Flasket,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Rob: Wilkinson.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon vpon occasion of the late rebellion.</note>
                  <note>C4 is a cancel; C4r line 3 ends "were". Variant: C4 is cancellandum; C4r line 3 ends "men".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:21761:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21761:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SERMON PREACHED at North-Hampton the 21. of Iune laſt paſt, before the Lord Lieutenant of the County, and the reſt of the Commiſſioners there aſſembled vpon occaſion of the late Rebellion and Riots in thoſe parts committed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prou. 22. 2</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The rich and the poore meete together, the Lord is the maker of them all.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Flasket: a garb or wheatsheaf on a wreath (McKerrow no. 356)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London for IOHN FLASKET. 1607.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21761:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21761:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honorable</hi> Thomas Earle of Exeter, Lord Baron of <hi>Burleigh, Knight of the moſt Noble Order</hi> of the Garter, one of his Maieſties most Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Priuy Councell, and Lord Lieutenant for the Countie <hi>of North-hampton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable: It is not long ſince I came forth in a Marchants ſhippe, and nowe it is Gods prouidence, and your good pleaſure, that I ſhall publiſh my ſelfe in a storme: In the appeaſing whereof, ſince it hath pleaſed your Honour to vſe my ſeruice as the word ioyned with the Sword, or rather as the Sword of the Spirit with the Sword of Iuſtice, I haue diſcharged my ſelfe as indifferently as I could to the cutting downe of offence in all: It is true that we are fallen into tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous and troubleſome times, wherein
<pb facs="tcp:21761:3"/> the exceſsiue couetouſneſſe of ſome hath cauſed extreame want to other, and that want not well diſgeſted hath riotted to the hazard of all; yea and by theſe ſtormes we are caſt among the rocks, euen two the moſt dangerous rocks of estate, Oppreſsion of the mighty, and Rebellion of the manie, by miſchiefe wherof many floriſhing king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and countries haue miſcarried, and ſo had we in this vndoubtedly, had not God by your good indeauors preuented it; &amp; therfore between theſe two rocks I ſaile, admoniſhing in the paſſage the one ſort, that is, the Mighty, <hi>that man liueth by bread,</hi> but the other ſort, that is, the Many <hi>that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liueth not by bread only,</hi> to the intent that they which know the ordinary courſe of God in preſeruing nature might make a conſcience of impairing the means of mans preſeruation, and they likewiſe which knowe that God hath wayes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue beyond the meanes of nature, might learne with chriſtian wiſdome &amp; patience to temper the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in want: And becauſe Right Honorable wee haue obtained great quietneſſe through you, &amp; your worthy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, and that great things are done vnto our countrie through your prouidence, God forbid, but that as <hi>Tertullus</hi> did to <hi>Foelix</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21761:3"/> ſo we much more to you ſhould acknowledge it wholy, &amp; in all places, &amp; with all thanks: yet in this we are bold to intreat you, that as you haue bin meanes for the due execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice vpon the rebellious, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (as opportunity ſhall ſerue) to promote the cauſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints of the expelled, halfe pined, and diſtreſſed poore, that they rebell no more. It is the end of al mens exaltation according to the proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſtate &amp; powre to do workes of mercy &amp; iuſtice, for he that ſat vpon a throne did confeſſe, that <hi>the thrones were ſet vp for iudgement</hi> Pſal. 122. Now iudgement looketh both wayes: and therfore as it chaſtiſeth the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor, ſo it repreſſeth him likewiſe, by whoſe couetouſnes &amp; cruelty the offence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth: eſpecially it will be looked for at your hands (Right honorable) ſtrongly to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the cauſe of <hi>corne</hi> &amp; of <hi>bread,</hi> God hauing giuen you a ſheafe ſupported with Lyons, as the higheſt top, &amp; chiefeſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of your Honor. Neither is there any greater promiſe of eſtabliſhment made to the families &amp; perſons of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious reſpect of the poore, which who ſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>his righteouſnes remaineth for euer, &amp; his horne ſhal be exalted with honor.</hi> Pſa. 112. God continue &amp; increaſe in you an affection of the one, that you
<pb facs="tcp:21761:4"/> may bee made partaker of the other. And thus in my deepest deuotion commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God your ſelfe, your ſtate, and honorable family, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors late Chaplaine, and ſtill deuoted in all Chriſtian duty. ROB: WILKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21761:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at North-Hampton <hi>vpon occaſion of the late Rebellion the</hi> 21. <hi>of Iune.</hi> 1607.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Math. 4. 4.</bibl> But hee anſwering ſayde: It is written, Man ſhall not liue by bread onely, but by euery word that proceedeth out off the mouth of GOD.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that ſaid the whole life of man was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a time of temptation, hee ſayd very fearefullie, and yet very truelie; for we are tempted in old age, and in our cradles wee are not free; If any euil ſtand before vs, we are prouoked to do it, and when at any time we haue done well, we are euen tempted in it; if wee abound as <hi>Adam</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21761:5"/> did in Paradiſe, there be intiſmentes in that, or if we want as Chriſt did in the wildernes, there may be death in that; ſo expert is the enemy whom God hath ſent to exerciſe vs, that according to time and place, &amp; to each mans ſtate &amp; nature, he hath wherin to allure vs, and ſerueth himſelf of al occaſions. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are fallen into a time, wherein pouerty without patience hath much diſordred vs, I haue therfore choſen to ſpeake of the hungry temptation, &amp; yet not of the temptation neither, each ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being apt enough to tempt himſelfe, but rather of the anſwer to it; for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel finding Chriſt of late, firſt faſting, &amp; then hungry in a deſolate &amp; barren wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe where nothing was to be had, aduiſeth him not to looke vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence in extreme want all help is to be waited for) but rather to take the way that was next at hand, &amp; by a new kind of Alchimy, of ſtones to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe bread, &amp; vnto this Chriſt anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him with the text I haue read, <hi>man liueth not by bread onely, &amp;c.</hi> and there is nothing in this whole ſtory ſo ſutable, or ſo aptly ſpeaking to the occaſion &amp; ſeaſon of the time as this; for it is ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:21761:5"/> before, that <hi>Chriſt faſted,</hi> meaning a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious faſt, as few do now; and it is ſaide likewiſe, that <hi>he was hungry,</hi> and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, for he was in a place, where was neither bred nor corn, as may be now; &amp; it is ſaid likewiſe, that <hi>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tempter came,</hi> that is, the Diuell came, as all the world ſeeth he is vp and abroad now; &amp; ſome he tempteth to turne bread into ſtones, that is, to decay the plenty of the earth, as many rich &amp; greedy minded me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do now; &amp; ſome he tempteth to turne ſtones into bread, that is, to vſe vnlawful means for their own releife, as the mad &amp; rebelious multitude doth now; but in this verſe Chriſt ſheweth a bettet way for mens reliefe, that is, by reſting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the pleaſure &amp; prouidence of God, which is for all men an apt &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwer, to ſuch a diuiliſh &amp; vngodlie temptation. In which anſwer 3. things may bee conſidered; firſt, that Chriſt would anſwer the Diuill, next the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his anſwer, which is by <hi>ſcriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi> &amp; then laſtly the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his anſwer, which is, that <hi>man liueth not by bread one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but by euery word which commeth out of the mouth of God.</hi> For the firſt, a queſtion may be mooued, why Chriſt would vouchſafe to giue the diuil any anſwer
<pb facs="tcp:21761:6"/> at all; why did hee not rather anſwer him with ſilence, as ſometimes he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Caiphas</hi> and <hi>Pilate?</hi> to which I anſwer, that as hee was therefore lead into the wilderneſſe, that he might bee tempted, ſo was he therefore tempted that he might giue anſwer, and that partly to auouch his owne wiſedome by his anſwer, and alſo to inſtruct vs, that we in the like caſe muſt bee able likewiſe to make anſwer; <hi>Reſpondit ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatori docens te reſpondere tentatori,</hi> ſaith <hi>Saint Auſtin;</hi> Chriſt did anſwer the tempter to teach thee, that thou muſt anſwer the tempter alſo; that as <hi>Gedeon</hi> ſayd to his ſouldiers, <hi>VVhat yee ſee mee doe, do yee alſo. Iudg.</hi> 7. 17. So wee becauſe wee ſee our Captaine to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, might alſo learne not <hi>Implicitam fidem,</hi> a faith folded vp in the faith of our fathers, or to beleeue as the Church beleeueth, but be armed with reaſon to anſwer alſo: In the field it is lamentable when the defendors of a iuſt and lawfull cauſe are foyled &amp; put to flight; <hi>O Lord, what ſhall I ſay</hi> (ſayth <hi>Ioſhua) when Iſrael turne their backes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their enemies? Ioſhu.</hi> 7. In the Church it is ſhamefull when men ſhall main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:21761:6"/> a good cauſe as <hi>Iob</hi> did, and yet being oppoſed cannot find an anſwer: and God forbid we ſhould auouch any things in points of faith, for which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppoſed we cannot anſwer. But in the breaſt of man it is moſt fearefull, when Satan ſhall come to tempt or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie, and we like <hi>Cain</hi> or <hi>Iudas</hi> are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome and cannot anſwer: for if we be bound <hi>to anſwer euery man that asketh a reaſon of the hope that is in vs.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. How much more to anſwer this temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and deſtroying Serpent, from whoſe temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no man can promiſe himſelfe freedom or imunity. But ſay, Chriſt would anſwer the Diuell, yet why after ſo milde and gentle a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion; why rather did hee not bid him be packing, as he did ſomtime to <hi>Peter? Get thee behind me Sathan, thou art an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence vnto me. Mat.</hi> 16. Yea why did he not torment him for his pride &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in tempting him? why did he not throw him into the deepe for laying vnholy hands, &amp; for breathing thoſe impure blaſts vpon him? &amp; thus we imagin God like our ſelues; for <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangell though hee ſtroue againſt the Diuell, yet would
<pb facs="tcp:21761:7"/> not reuile him. <hi>Iud.</hi> 9. nor would Chriſt call for fire from heauen to conſume the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> albeit they ſhut their dores vpon him. <hi>Luc.</hi> 9. for he came not now to iudge, but to ſaue; he came not (as one day he ſhall) with fire before him, but he came like a Lambe, lowly to his inferiors, gentle to his enemies, and affable to all; which firſt addeth ſtrength to the faith of man, in the act of Inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for if the enemy receiued a gentle anſwer, euen when he came to deſtroy, much more ſhall they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly ſeeke vnto him; beſide, it giueth to great perſonages, Iudges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in their places, an honorable patterne of piety, cheerfully to accept, &amp; gently to anſwer, the cries, petitions &amp; iuſt complaints of the poore, which ſtand in need of them, as they ſtand in need of God, &amp; come kneeling to them as they kneele to God; &amp; when at any time they grow weary of this, they may doubt they haue forgotten him who exalted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for this, &amp; feare leaſt they be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they faile in this. Now for the maner of Chriſts anſwer to the diuill; ye ſee, he doth not teach vs to repell or chaſe him away (as they do at <hi>Rome,</hi> with Tapers, &amp; holy water,
<pb facs="tcp:21761:7"/> or with hanging out a crucifix, but by <hi>ſcriptum eſt,</hi> the written word of God; for what cares the diuill for a candle, or for holy water, or what cares he for a Crucifix, which is but an image of Chriſt, who according to ſome of their own doctors did not feare to lay foule <note place="margin">Hugo Cardin. ſup. Math 4. Aſſumpſit eum bracchijs ſuis.</note> hands vpon the ſacred body of Chriſt: but as when <hi>Ioſhua</hi> fained to run away from the men of <hi>Ai,</hi> hee did by that meanes diſranke them, &amp; bring a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſlaughter on them. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. ſo when the diuill faineth to be afraide of ſuch things, it is but a ſlie deuiſe, to wrappe men more deeply in the ſnares of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. Neither yet doth Chriſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Diuill by <hi>Factum eſt,</hi> by doing the thing required, that is, turning ſtones into bread, but hee anſwereth him by <hi>ſcriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi> by ſhewing him what is written; no doubt Chriſt could haue turned the ſtones, and the ſtones being commanded muſt haue obeied him, for when the Prophet cryed out againſt <hi>Ieroboams</hi> altar, <hi>the aſhes fell out, and the Altar rent in ſunder.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 13. but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a greater then the Prophet was here, who when himſelfe cryed out his laſt crye vpon the Croſſe, the vale of the Temple rent, the earth did
<pb facs="tcp:21761:8"/> quake, &amp; the ſtones did cleaue in ſunder <hi>Math.</hi> 27. yea ſurely hee that of water made wine, could alſo (if it had ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him) of ſtones haue made bread; yea he could of ſtones haue made men, euen of ſtones to raiſe vp children vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraham, Math.</hi> 3. but why then did he not? ſurely the Friers tell vs a prety reaſon; That Chriſt would not turne ſtones into bread at the diuels requeſt, <note place="margin">Royard. Dominica. 1. Quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſimae.</note> but rather ſtay a yeare longer to turne water into wine, at his Mothers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that ſo to her, to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and not to the Diuill, might be dedicated the firſt fruites of his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as if Chriſt had dedicated mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles to his Mother, or had in the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of water turned to wine, intended the magnifying of his Mother, who when ſhee mooued vnto him the want of wine, receaued an anſwer ſome-thing regardleſſe of her; <hi>VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man what haue I to doe with thee? Ioh.</hi> 2. 4. but a better reaſon of that miracle is gathered out of the eleuenth verſe, where it is ſayde, the miracle being done, that <hi>his Diſciples beleeued on him;</hi> but how? <hi>Nunquid crediturus erat dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolus?</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> would the
<pb facs="tcp:21761:8"/> Diuill haue beleeued if Chriſt had turned ſtones into bread? ſurely no; and therefore as he would ſhew no miracle to <hi>Herod,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he asked it idly and curiouſly, <hi>Luc.</hi> 23. ſo neither is any miracle to bee ſhewed to the Diuill, nor any Pearle to be caſt before ſuch Swine, as there is no hope to conuert or edifie; or ſay there were hope, yet <hi>Scriptum est,</hi> the Law and the Prophets are more effectuall (ſaith <hi>Abraham)</hi> then if one ſhould riſe from the dead; yea if they will not heare <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, neither will they bee perſwaded, though one riſe from the dead. <hi>Luc.</hi> 16. and generally by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt, it is ſo much better to contend with authority of ſcriptures, then with powre of miracles, by how much Chriſt preferred <hi>Scriptum est,</hi> before tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtones into bread. Neither yet doth Chriſt anſwer the Diuill by vnwritten ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, as they do who thruſt vpon the faith of men, dreames, and fables, and meere tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, which is (ſaith <hi>Theodoret)</hi> like the <note place="margin">Theodoret. queſt. 9. in Leuit.</note> ſinne of <hi>Araons</hi> ſonnes, to bring ſtrange fire vpon the Altar. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10. but he anſwereth him by <hi>Scriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi> It is written; &amp; if it be not written, it is ſure no matter of faith, but men may chooſe whether they wil beleeue it or no: but if it be written, men muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, and build their faith, their ſoules,
<pb facs="tcp:21761:9"/> and ſaluation vpon it; <hi>for therefore yee erre</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>becauſe yee know not the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Mat.</hi> 22. but he that knoweth them, knoweth alſo all needful wiſdom in them; for ſpeake we of matters of faith; <hi>Fidem Imperator queris;</hi> ſaith <hi>Hilary</hi> to <hi>Conſtance</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hilar: ad Conſtant:</note> the Emperor, <hi>Seeke yee to know the faith;</hi> then muſt ye vnderſtand it, not by any new or late writings, but by the bookes of <hi>God.</hi> Or ſeeke yee to know which is the true &amp; catholique church? <hi>Nullo modo cognoſcitur, niſi tantummodo per ſcripturas,</hi> there is no <note place="margin">Chriſoſt. homil. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Math. &amp; 46.</note> way to know it ſaith <hi>S. Chryſoſt.</hi> but only by the ſcriptures: or groweth ther any doubt or controuerſie of opinion in the church? we may ſay to one another, as <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> to <note place="margin">Aug. contra Maximin. lib. 3. ca. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Maximinus</hi> the <hi>Arrian, Nec ego Nicenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi, nec tu mihi Ariminenſe debes proferre conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</hi> neither wil I obiect to you the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Nice,</hi> nor ſhall you to me the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Ariminu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> but let the Scriptures end it; for (eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our enemies being iudges) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is in queſtion whether ſuch a thing bee lawfull or no, <hi>Ad ſacram pagina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recurrendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi> we muſt haue recourſe to th'holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſaith <hi>Stella ſup: Luc.</hi> 6. 3. becauſe in them we may find, <hi>Sufficienter et veraciter,</hi> both ſufficiently &amp; truly, <hi>Omnia que ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem ſunt neceſſaria,</hi> euen al things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer are needfull to ſaluation, ſaith <hi>Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentura</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21761:9"/> 
               <hi>de profectu religioſor. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. both theſe men being Friers and fautors of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet againſt the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> maintaining ſincerely the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of the ſcriptures; Therefore theſe are the weapons of our warfare; <hi>ſcriptum eſt:</hi> the word of God (ſaith <hi>S. Paul)</hi> is the ſword of the ſpirit. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. yea this is the ſword of the Lord and of <hi>Gedeon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſubſtance of this anſwer is, that <hi>Man liueth not by bread only, but by euery word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.</hi> The place is found. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 3. where <hi>Moſes</hi> exhorting the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> in al their wants to depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the prouidence of God, putteth them in mind, how that being in the wildernes, where was neither bread nor water, yet were they neither famiſht with want, nor yet compelled to vſe vnlawfull means for their reliefe, but they had a bread which they knew not, euen <hi>Manna</hi> ſent from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as in a tipe to ſhew, that mans life is maintained not by the means of bread, nor by the fruitfulneſſe of the earth, but from the houſe of Prouidence, that is, from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and this doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> oppoſe as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Diuil, wherin 2. things may be diſtinctly conſidered, Firſt that man liueth by bread, and then ſecondly that he liueth not by bread onely, that is, that God hath appointed man to liue by means, &amp; yet he
<pb facs="tcp:21761:10"/> hath not tied his life vnto the meanes. That <hi>man liueth by bread,</hi> is inferred out of the very text; for euen where he ſaith, <hi>Not by bread onely,</hi> it followeth of neceſsitie, that amongſt other meanes, yet by bread for one &amp; there be in theſe words three things likewiſe to be conſidered; Firſt the ſubiect of God; prouidence, which is <hi>Man</hi> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of Gods prouidence, that <hi>man must liue:</hi> and thirdly the meanes of his prouidence, that he muſt liue <hi>by bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, the diuil indeed propounded very cunningly a queſtion concerning the ſonne of God; <hi>If thou bee the ſonne of God, command, &amp;c:</hi> which yet Chriſt neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth, nor affirmeth himſelfe to bee, but cleane beſide the matter, anſwereth of man; <hi>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liueth not;</hi> &amp; ſure Chriſt was not bound to giue direct anſwer to ſuch an aduerſary, who came not to bee ſatiſfied, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, and therfore to dazell and amaze him the more, he anſwereth him at randome, &amp; where he asked him of the ſonne of God, he anſwere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h him of man, and to let him ſee withal, what account God did make of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom he in tempting the ſonne of God, ſought fundamentally to ouerthrow. And ſurely man is a great marke in Gods eie, for God made man, &amp; printed his owne image in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; made the world for man, &amp; ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:21761:10"/> the Angels to gard man, was borne for man, and in the end dyed for man, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> breakes out into admiration, <hi>VVhat is man, that thou art ſo mindfull of him, or the Sonne of man that thou regardeſt him. Pſal.</hi> 8. Onely man to man is vile and of no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, &amp; man is <hi>Anthropomaſtix,</hi> one man the greateſt ſcourge &amp; plague of another. <hi>Man liueth,</hi> ſayth Chriſt; therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion is here made for man, which may ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine in this place a two-fold oppoſition, firſt with the beaſts and brute creatures, before which in Gods prouidence Man is euer preferred, &amp; then ſecondly with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men, for <hi>Man</hi> is not here taken for this or that man, but for <hi>Humanum genus,</hi> Man for all mankind, &amp; ſo it ſtandeth with reaſon that the whole kinde be evermore preferred before any one or a few cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants in their kinde.</p>
            <p>If yee ſpeak of the beaſts; ſurely to that queſtion of S. <hi>Paul, Doth God take care for Oxen.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. We may anſwer affirmatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yes ſure euen for Oxen, and for ſheep, for ſo ſaith <hi>Dauid. Pſal.</hi> 36. <hi>Thou Lord doſt ſaue Man and Beaſt;</hi> yea and for little birds too, whereof two are ſold for a farthing, <note place="margin">Deut. 22. 6</note> euen the great God hath made protectiue lawes, that man ſhould not deale vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully with them: yet we muſt take this
<pb facs="tcp:21761:11"/> withall, that whatſoeuer God hath done for the beaſts, yet is it not for their owne ſakes principally, but for mans, for whoſe vſe and ſeruice they were created, &amp; not for them ſelues; and is it not then vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall (thinke ye) to ſee a man put out, to put in a beaſt, and men turned out to bring in ſheepe, whereas God created the earth for men, and not for ſheepe; therefore if ye will maintaine large paſtures and ſtock them with ſheepe, then remember what God ſaith by the mouth of <hi>Ezechiel, The ſheepe of my paſture are men. Eze.</hi> 34. 31. yea <hi>and we are his people and the ſheepe of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. Pſal.</hi> 100. and the image of God in one man is more worth then all the ſheep in the world: and it is time, yea high time to ſpeake of this, the text of it already being written in bloud; and no maruell if they which feele it, runne madde and wild vpon it, ſince wee which but ſee it are ſo much amazed at it; for a ſtranger which coaſteth theſe countries, and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth heere and there ſo many thouſands and thouſands of ſheepe, <hi>&amp; nihil humani generis,</hi> in ſo many miles not a thing like a Man, might take vp a wonder, &amp; ſay with himſelfe; what? hath there bin ſome Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereſſe, or ſome <hi>Circe</hi> heere that hath transformed men into beaſts? or is it ſo,
<pb facs="tcp:21761:11"/> that men and beaſts haue waged warre to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether! but how was this battell fought, that ſheepe got the field? or what men were theſe that ranne away from ſheepe? yea rather what ſheepe were theſe that throw down houſes, townes, &amp; churches? oh no: theſe were no ſheepe, they were hogges by their rooting, ye forget him that made the world for man.</p>
            <p>Or be it that in this depopulation the beaſts did not ouergo man, yet whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is done to the waſting of mankind for the benefit of a few in the kind, is againſt the prouidence of God too: for God ſaid not to <hi>Adam</hi> and to <hi>Eue</hi> at the firſt, <hi>Increaſe,</hi> but <hi>Increaſe and multiply, yea &amp; fill the earth. Gen.</hi> 1. 28. Fill it: how? not with clamors and with cries, with teares and with bloud, with mutinies and implacable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion as theſe men doe; but fill it with men, with the image of God, with the precious ſeede of the diuine generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and ſeeke not (as the Prophet ſayth) by ioyning houſe to houſe, and land to land to bee alone vpon the earth. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 5. Nor let your ſhepheardes ſay to you as <hi>Diogines</hi> ſometime ſaid to <hi>Timon,</hi> O that there were none but thou &amp; I in the land; for in the end <hi>Timon</hi> will ſay to <hi>Diogines</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I like the wiſh well, ſo as when <hi>Diogines</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21761:12"/> 
               <hi>thy brother, that thy brother may liue with thee.</hi> Not meaning that vſury did kill men, but that it doth vndoe men, and vndoing is a wofull kinde of dying; for when a man dies, he is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, and when he is buryed perhaps he is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, yet they that lamented him ſuruiue ſtill, but when a man is vndon, hee dies in his eſtate, he dies in his reputation, he dies in his wife and children, &amp; his whole houſe is like hell, euen a heape of miſery, his cattell looke poorely like <hi>Pharaos</hi> leane Kine; his Cartes driue heauilie like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Chariots with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wheeles; and his creditors follow him, as <hi>Pharao</hi> followed the <hi>Iſralites</hi> at their backs; ſo as ſuch a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſeeme to liue in <hi>Aegipt;</hi> nay it were better by farre, to ſit downe &amp; make bricks in <hi>Aegipt;</hi> for this is not liuing, but lingring death, &amp; many to auoid this, chooſe rather to die. Therfore marke I beſeech you; yee, to whom God hath giuen the Earth in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; <hi>learne to be mercifull as your heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Father is mercifull.</hi> For when God at the <note place="margin">Luke. 6. 36</note> beginning made man, firſt <hi>he breathed in his face the breath of life,</hi> and then immediatlie <hi>he put him into the Garden which he had made Geneſ.</hi> 2. 7. 8. as much as to ſay, that firſt God gaue man life, and then preſently gaue him liuing; yea Paradiſe was planted firſt, and Man created after; ſo carefull was God, not onely of Mans life, but alſo of his liuing,
<pb facs="tcp:21761:12"/> that the thing which maintained him was made before him, for if hee had giuen him life before liuing, the Father of prouidence ſhould haue ſeemed to deale vnprouidently, but if he had giuen him life without liuing, the father of mercy ſhould haue created his children vnto miſery. And if ye thinke it no ſin to take away the liuing where God hath giuen life, ye may think it a leſſe ſin to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way life, when ye haue taken away the liuing. And let it be a leſſon for all ſtates generally, not <hi>to grind the faces of the poore:</hi> but the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <note place="margin">Eſa. 3.</note> ſo to wage his ſeruant that he may liue; &amp; the work-maſter ſo to wage the laborer, that he may liue, &amp; the land-lord not to rack, but ſo to rate his tenant that he may liue, not miſerably, for ſo it were better to die, but as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues liue plentifully vnder God, ſo they ſufficiently &amp; contentedly vnder them; For let men be ſo oppreſſed, that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not liue, &amp; then they come to the cry of the Steward, when hee was put out off his Steward-ſhip; <hi>What ſhall I do! Luk.</hi> 16. and it is fearefull to thinke, what men will doe in the end. <hi>His Maiſter puttes him out off the Steward-ſhippe,</hi> and how then? <hi>I cannot digge</hi> (ſaith hee) and yet now yee ſee men can digge when they bee put out: and <hi>to begge I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;</hi> yet Men are now aſhamed of nothing yea affrayd of nothing, but deſperate eſtates breed
<pb facs="tcp:21761:13"/> they haue turned not ſtones into bread, but corne into graſſe, and done for a practiſe that which God threatned for a plague, To take away the ſtaffe of bread; yea they haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as <hi>Achab</hi> did with <hi>Micaiah,</hi> the bread of food, into the <hi>bread of affliction.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 22. and worſe then ſo, they haue turned men into beaſts, and made them wilde and rebellious, which before were tame and obedient; yea &amp; worſe then ſo, they haue turned liuing bodies into dead carkaſes, which though they haue iuſtly periſht in their rebellion; yet as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Luc.</hi> 17. <hi>Woe be to them by whom the offence commeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next point of the anſwer is, that though God haue appointed man to liue by bread, yet not by bread onely. Commonly wee are thus affected to the outward meanes, that if at any time they faile vs, we are ready to curſe, and finally to renounce them, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for the ſinew that ſhranke in <hi>Iacobs</hi> thigh, <note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> vowed neuer to eate of the ſinew any more: but when they ſtand vs in ſteed, and doe their ſeuerall offices to vs, we are ready, as the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptians</hi> did with their Sheepe and Oxen, to deifie and make gods of them, &amp; euen to ſay, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. <hi>Theſe are thy Gods which brought thee, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore to draw men from immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate admiration of theſe inferior meanes, Chriſt telleth vs, that though <hi>by bread,</hi> yet
<pb facs="tcp:21761:13"/> 
               <hi>not by bread onely;</hi> for to effect things alone is proper to GOD onely, who onely can ſay, as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 63. <hi>I haue troden the Wine-preſſe alone, and of all the people there was none with me:</hi> and if man ſhould liue by bread onely, then were bread his God; and therefore euen the ſame mouth which commendeth to vs the labours of our hands, condemneth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all confidence in our owne endeuours; for euen in the Church where Gods owne worke is done, yet planting of it ſelfe, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of it ſelfe is nothing; In policies, and in the common-wealth, <hi>Except the Lord keepe the Citty, the watch-man watcheth but in vaine:</hi> and they which asked a King to gouerne them, yet were no whit better, but rather in worſe caſe when they had him; Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the field, <hi>A Horſe is a vaine thing to ſaue a man;</hi> and though a Bowe and a Sworde bee mighty weapons in the hands of the mightie, yet <hi>I will not trust in my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Bowe, nor ſhall my Sworde ſaue mee,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, in priuate Families, and in domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call affaires, <hi>It is in vaine for men to riſe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and goe to bedde late:</hi> yea and in the very body of man, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> which ſo luſted for meate, yet when they had meate, dyed with meate in their mouthes. <hi>Number.</hi> 11. yea and many, the more they haue, the
<pb facs="tcp:21761:14"/> worſe they thriue, like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> leane Kine which did eate vp the fatte, and yet were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the fatter when they had done; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though much may be done by bread, yet nothing by bread onely.</p>
            <p>Well then; If not by bread onely, by what then? <hi>By euery word that proceedeth out off the mouth of God;</hi> where becauſe mention is made of <hi>euery word,</hi> wee are to conſider, that the word of God is manifold whereby wee liue, for firſt there is <hi>Verbum ſcriptum:</hi> the written word of God, which feedes vs with wiſdom, ſecondly there is the word of his bleſsing, which ſtrengthneth with goodneſſe; thirdly the word of eſpeciall power which mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth by miracle; fourthly the word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which ſupporteth by faith; &amp; laſtly euen the word of deniall which vpholdeth vs in patience.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If we ſpeake of the written word or of the Scripture, it is true that man liueth not by bread onely, but by that too; for <hi>Search the ſcriptures</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>for they are they which teſtifie of me, and in them yee ſhall haue life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Iohn.</hi> 5. And it is a good barre againſt the Diuells temptation, when hee telleth vs of bread, and turning ſtones into bread, and all for bread, to tell him againe, that there is ſomewhat elſe to be cared for beſide bread, that becauſe God hath giuen vs a ſoule to
<pb facs="tcp:21761:14"/> ſaue, as well as a body to feed, and a belly to fill, that wee therefore ſhould rather care to feed and inſtruct the ſoule, then to pamper the body; eſpecially to inſtruct the ſoule thus farre againſt the body, that we may learne to do no vnlawfull thing for natures neceſſity, nor to hazard an immortall ſoule, for a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and dying body; And had many of vs beene as well inſtructed in the word of God, and in their duty to God, the King &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as they haue beene in the word of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and in vnlawfull meanes of recouering bread, I thinke want of bread could neuer haue raiſed ſuch wicked tumults as it hath; but a man may truly ſay to the moſt hungry ſoule of this tumultuous company, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was moſt oppreſſed, and moſt hungry, yet euen then he was better fed then taught.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly if ye ſpeake of, <hi>Verbum benedictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> the word of his bleſſing; it is true, that man liueth not by bread onely, but chiefelie by the bleſſing of God, <hi>for euery creature</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Paul) is ſanctified by the word of God.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. that is by the bleſſing of God, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Theodoret</hi> expound it. And this appeareth to vs three wayes, Firſt becauſe the very ſame thing bleſſed and not bleſſed, doth ſhew forth powre accordingly, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. when againſt the commandement of God they reſerued of the <hi>Mannah</hi> till the morning, it putrified and
<pb facs="tcp:21761:15"/> ſtanke, yet the very ſame <hi>Mannah</hi> being kept by the commandement of God, was ſweet &amp; good many yeares in the Arke; the reaſon of which difference was becauſe God did giue his bleſſing to the one, and denied it to the other; Secondly, whereas we by proportion feed our families, as <hi>Dauid</hi> when he feaſted the people, gaue to euery one a peece of fleſh, &amp; a Cake of bread; 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. that is, ſo many Cakes of bread to ſo many people, yet God when hee pleaſeth, without all proportion feedeth man; for <hi>Math.</hi> 15. with ſeauen loues he fed 4000. which was much, but <hi>Math.</hi> 14. with 5. loaues he fed 5000. which was much more; the miracle was great when it was at the leaſt, but with the leſſe prouiſion to feede the greater number maketh it much greater; but the ſtrangeſt miracle is in the fragments, yea in the fragments three great miracles ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared; firſt that out of ſo ſmall a portion fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo many, there ſhould come any frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at al, next that out of the fewer loaues and the greater number to be fed, there did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe the more fragments; &amp; laſtly that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundance of the fragments was more then the firſt ſtock or principall ſtore of bread; &amp; what is all this, but the bleſſing of God? Thirdly, (which the diuill here acknowledgeth) God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when it pleaſeth him, put the very ſtrength of bread into a ſtone, yea he that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:21761:15"/> of a ſtone, can feed him with a ſtone, &amp; nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh him more with meate of leſſe nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then with the more, as <hi>Daniel</hi> &amp; the reſt, which liued with water &amp; pulſe, <hi>had their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces not ſo faire, but fairer then they which liued of the Kings owne table. Dan.</hi> 1. and what is this likewiſe but the bleſſing of God: And had we not tied our life to bread, and thought God could not haue bleſſed vs, but by filling our bellyes, wee ſhould neuer haue forſaken the bleſſing of God, to haue falne into the curſe of thoſe conſpiring brethren, <hi>Curſed be their wrath, for it was fierce, &amp;c. Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 49. but it ſeemeth that theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when they had bread, they had it without the bleſſing of God, &amp; wanted grace to vſe it, and therefore now hauing no bread, they want another bleſſing, &amp; know not how to want it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, if yee ſpeake of <hi>verbum potentiae,</hi> the word of his powre; that word whereof it is ſaid, <hi>he ſpake the word, and it was done,</hi> it is true likewiſe that man liueth not by bread onely but many times by the ſpecial powre of God; which appeareth alſo three waies; firſt by rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vp of extraordinary meanes, as when the Iſraelites were in the wilderneſſe where the earth did yeeld no bread, the Lord did cauſe euen the heauen to do the office of the earth, &amp; to raine downe bread. Secondly, as he doth ſtrangely prouide bread, ſo when it pleaſeth him hee can preſerue life without bread, for <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21761:16"/> of faith; for <hi>to him that beleeueth all things are poſsible. Mark.</hi> 9. Therefore if yee will haue bread, conſpire not in mutinies, but conſpire in mutuall prayers; roote not vp harmeleſſe hedges, nor rend vp the bowells of the earth; but looke vp to heauen from whence yee ſhall haue bread; and though yee ſee no meanes how, yea though yee ſee reaſon to deſpayre, yet yee ſhall haue bread; for hee hath ſaid it who cannot deceiue, that <hi>hee will not affamiſh the ſoule of the righteous. Pro.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly and laſtly as there is <hi>Verbum promit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens,</hi> a word of promiſe to reſt vpon, and euery man of ordinary faith can ſtay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on that, ſo is there likewiſe <hi>Verbum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negans,</hi> a word of deniall, whereby God ſaith ſometimes, ye ſhall haue no bread at all, and (which is the higheſt point of religion) we muſt learne to ſtand faſt euen in that too; Thus ſtood <hi>Dauid</hi> in that great diſtreſſe by <hi>Abſolon, If I ſhall finde fauour in the eies of the Lord, hee will bring me againe, but if he ſay thus I haue no delight in thee, behold heere I am, let him doe as ſeemeth him good.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 25. 26. Thus affected likewiſe ſtood the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in their fiery tryall, <hi>Our God whom we ſerue is able, yea and will deliuer vs out off thy handes, but if not, yet bee it knowne vnto thee, that wee will not ſerue thy Gods &amp;c. Dan.</hi> 3, 17. 18. And <hi>Iob</hi> in the higheſt ſtile and
<pb facs="tcp:21761:16"/> ſtrength of patience, <hi>Though hee kill mee, yet will I truſt in him. Iob.</hi> 13. 15. For though God bee alwayes mercifull to giue, yet in his wiſedome hee will not giue alwayes, but ſometime hee will ſuffer, yea hee will ſend men to take it from vs, for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our patience, the tryall of our fayth and for the conſummating the ſinnes of the cruell; and no maruell if it be thus now, that the cruell and tyrannos, or as <hi>Eliphas</hi> ſayth, <hi>The mighty, and men of authority haue the earth in poſſeſsion. Iob.</hi> 22. 8. For thus it hath beene euer, and thus it will be alwayes; and as the the Apoſtle ſayth of the Church <hi>Oportet eſſe haereſes, there muſt bee hereſies.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. ſo ſaith Chriſt of the world, <hi>Vae mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do a ſcandalis, wo to the world becauſe of offences, yet can it not bee auoyded but that offences will come. Mat.</hi> 18. yea it were rather to be maruailed at, if offences ſhould not come, or that the world ſhould bee in better ſtate then it is, the Diuell beeing the God, and gouernor of it; But how then? ſhall wee therefore ſhake off patience, and renounce obedience, and take the ſword into our owne handes, becauſe GOD will not plant another paradiſe heere, and make the world as wee would haue it? Now ſure it is an eaſie thing to hope when we haue it at hand, and to bee patient and quiet
<pb facs="tcp:21761:17"/> when we lacke nothing, and euery man hath thus much religion, when God giueth him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, to bleſſe him for it: but to ſay with <hi>Iob, The Lord giueth, and the Lord taketh,</hi> and then <hi>Bleſſed be the name of the Lord:</hi> This is the perfection of religion, euen patience it ſelfe: and <hi>we muſt in pacience poſſeſſe our ſoules. Luke.</hi> 21. and if we be not patient in our triall, all other our Religion is nothing. Neither yet do <hi>famine and nakednes ſeperate vs from Chriſt. Rom.</hi> 8. 35. But they bring vs neerer vnto Chriſt, and death neereſt of all, ſince it is the neceſſary office of Chriſtian loue <hi>for Chriſts ſake to be killed. verſ.</hi> 36. and when wee are killed, yet are we more then conquerors, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. It was truely ſayd, <hi>non ſunt hoc tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore finita, ſed mutata martyria,</hi> martyrdome is not now ended, but onely changed, for in time paſt men were martyred for profeſſion of faith: but now they may bee martyrs in the preſeruation of their charitie, yea wee may be Martyrs ſaith (S. <hi>Gregorie) ſine ferro &amp; ſanguine,</hi> though neither ſword touch vs, nor bloud come from vs: &amp; how is that? <hi>Si pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veraciter in animo cuſtodimus,</hi> if faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we keepe patience in our mindes: and we may ſay to the oppreſſors of our time, as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> ſaid to the tyrants and perſecutors of his time, <hi>Nobis ignominia non eſt pati a fratri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp;c.</hi> It is no ſhame to vs to ſuffer of our
<pb facs="tcp:21761:17"/> bretheren what Chriſt ſuffered, nor glory to you to play that part which <hi>Iudas</hi> played; yea rather with <hi>Tertullian, Crudelitas veſtra gloria noſtra,</hi> the more cruelly yee afflict vs, the more yee honor vs.</p>
            <p>Therefore marke (good people) what honor God had offered to vs, if patiently wee had borne the oppreſſion which is put vpon vs, for by this reckoning depopulators are perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, &amp; oppreſſion is perſecution, &amp; we by oppreſſion had come to martyrdome, if pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently we had borne it. But heauen &amp; earth are witneſſes how farre we are from bearing; yea bearing is come to bearding, and becauſe of a little want, men haue buried their patience as they buried hedges. Yea we are come to ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Manaſſes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ephraim;</hi> &amp; now at laſt we are come to flat reſiſting; The Thiſtle that is in <hi>Lebanon,</hi> to the Cedar that is in <hi>Lebanon; Come let vs ſee one another in the face;</hi> And as if brambles had bin annointed Kings, an inferiour Magiſtrate is now too meane, but the great King muſt come to compound himſelfe; or if he will not come, yet he muſt ſend <hi>A latere,</hi> a meſſenger from his royall ſide; or if a <hi>Harold</hi> come, It is an eaſie matter to ſend a painted coate; and when a Proclamation came, as good made vnder a hedge; and that which is horrible to ſpeake; A King of three great kingdomes
<pb facs="tcp:21761:18"/> muſt capitulate with a Tinker, whether by Proclamation or by priuy Seale hee ſhall manifeſt his will and pleaſure: and yet all this is called Reforming; but ſuch <hi>Rephaims</hi> are <hi>Zanzummims,</hi> which as <hi>Plato</hi> told <hi>Diogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> he did tread vpon his pride, <hi>Sed maiori cum faſtu,</hi> but with a greater pride, ſo theſe men reformed wickednes, but with far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wickednes; &amp; whereas <hi>Rehoboam</hi> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his little finger to be bigger then his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loynes, ſurely theſe mens little finger would haue bin bigger in the end the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rehobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> loines, for tyranny indeed is heauy in the hands of a King, but it is intollerable in times of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motion, when euery vile &amp; baſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a King; &amp; to ſpeak indifferently, I think the ſin of theſe men by many degrees to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the other, for Paſture-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indeed do hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible miſchiefe, but they do it by degrees; firſt one breaks the law; and then an other is bold to break it by example; now euils of ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage are more eaſily preuented; but that which growes by mutinies being ſodaine &amp; violent, is leſſe reſiſtible. Paſture-men indeed deſtroy a few townes, but mutiners by ciuill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motion depopulate whole kingdoms, and that partly by making way to forraine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who vſually increaſe their dominions by ſuch aduantage, but chiefely by ſacking &amp; harrying their owne country with their own
<pb facs="tcp:21761:18"/> hands. And let men ſet what pretence &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour they will, yet this hath bin from time to time the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon proceeding of popular mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies; firſt to murmure vpon ſome iuſt cauſe, as the <hi>Iſralites</hi> did at <hi>Moſes</hi> when he brought them where was neither water to drinke, nor bread to eat. <hi>Ex.</hi> 15. 24. &amp; <hi>Ex.</hi> 16. 3. Afterward when they had both to eate &amp; to drinke, yet <hi>(Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 11.) they murmured, not for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but for wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, <hi>viz.</hi> for fiſh, &amp; for fleſh, for apples, &amp; for cowcumbers &amp;c. Euen as many of our maleco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tents do now, who want not to drink, but want to make them dayly drunk. But <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b.</hi> 14. their murmuring came to that, that they would change the ſtate, they would put off <hi>Moſes,</hi> and haue an other to guide them: But <hi>Nomb.</hi> 16. in <hi>Coraths</hi> conſpiracy they came to that, that all the congregation was holy, they were all <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes, and they would haue no head at all; right as in the daies of the <hi>Iudges,</hi> wherein <hi>there was no King in Iſraell, but euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did what was right in his owne eyes. Iud.</hi> 17. 6. Thus we find in Scriptures, thus in ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yea and thus in our owne <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtories, and I do not thinke it would haue bin other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe now, vnleſſe it had bin worſe; For marke I beſeech ye, the courſe of this creeping con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie; firſt they bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the night, as checkt with feare &amp; conſcience of a crime, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e forth in the broad day, as fleſht and
<pb facs="tcp:21761:19"/> in this conſpiracie ſome one quarrell had ceaſed, yet the reſt had run riot ſtill; and then they which aroſe only to fill vp ditches, muſt perhaps haue beene compelled to entrench themſelues a new from other conſpirators: Nay let me ſay more as <hi>Eliſeus</hi> to his man, <hi>Is this a time to take bribes?</hi> to ſpeake ſimply, <note place="margin">2. Kin. 5.</note> there was no time at all for ſuch a worke, but at that time it was worſt of all, when ſome hope was offred of bringing home an idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour to the Church; ſo let me aske of theſe good people; Was this a time of all times to diſturbe the peace of the land; now that King and ſtate were ſo earneſt in hand to vnite two kingdoms into one, now to attempt the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of one kingdome into two? into two? nay into ten; into ten thouſand; and to bring it, not as <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2. 28. <hi>So many Citties ſo many Gods,</hi> but ſo many men ſo many Kings, and to make confuſion of all; but as the ſaying is, <hi>Melius eſt vt pereat vnus, quam vnitas;</hi> better one or a few to be puniſht, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hazarded; and if in this proceeding any haue miſcaried, they haue periſhed right, as <hi>Saint Iude</hi> ſaith, <hi>euen in the gaine-ſaying of Core. Iud.</hi> 11. and they haue left this behind them, that they were not killed, but as they killed themſelues, the ſword after a ſtrange maner asking peace of naked men, and mercy which ſhould be ſought, yet ſeeking for admiſſion
<pb facs="tcp:21761:19"/> with Cap in hand, and as it were creeping on her knees; and ſo for the reſt we leaue them to God. And if any yet remaine whom the poiſon of this conſpiracie hath infected; I will not vſe many reaſons to diſwade him; onely let him take this for one, that if the bleeding bodies of theſe ſlaughtered men did acknowledge, euen as they lay bleeding and groning their laſt vpon the ground, that they neuer felt they had offended God in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent act till then, but then they did; and ſome vpon the gallowes asked pardon of God, and confeſſed themſelues penitent for that they had done: what a fearefull thing were it for vs to liue in that ſinne, which theſe poore wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches deteſted when they dyed? therefore let vs not tie knots which we muſt vntie againe, nor commit that euill wherof we muſt againe repent vs, but rather bee thankfull for thoſe good things we haue, &amp; waite with patience for thoſe which yet wee haue not, and ſay in all things with Chriſt, <hi>Thy will be done,</hi> that ſo at the laſt his kingdome may come, euen the kingdome of righteouſneſſe and grace in this life, and that of glory in the next.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <salute>Pax in Chriſto.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
